Guide to the Solomon Pimsleur Papers 1918-1970
Washington State University Libraries Manuscripts, Archives, and Special Collections
Solomon Pimsleur Papers
1918-1970
Washington State University Libraries, Manuscripts, Archives, and Special Collections Pullman, WA 99164-5610 USA (509) 335-6691 http://www.wsulibs.wsu.edu/masc/ mascref@wsu.edu
Cage 478
Pimsleur, Solomon
7 containers. 8 linear feet of shelf space. 4100 items.
Correspondence and other papers, musical sketches and scores, recordings and microfilms, also paintings and drawings.
Solomon Pimsleur was born in Paris, France, in 1900 and emigrated to the United States with his parents at an early age. Completing both his undergraduate and graduate studies at Columbia University he was the recipient of a Julliard Fellowship in 1926 and studied at the Summer Institute of the Mozarteum, Salzburg, Austria, in 1929. An honorary D. Mus. was awarded to him by the Boguslawski College of Music in Chicago in 1940. He died in New York City in 1962. With over 120 compositions to his credit, Pimsleur can be considered a prolific composer. His work aroused some early attention, but he gained little recognition later in his life. Nor did he ever succeed in securing an academic position. A performance of his Symphonic Ballade by the Philharmonic Society of New York at Lewisohn Stadium in 1933 marked the sole performance of any of his works by an established professional ensemble. Subsequent performances of his compositions were in large part due to his own persistent efforts. While his compositions drew praise for the craftsmanship they exhibited, Pimsleur's self-declared conservative style put his music outside the mainstream of contemporary development. A posthumous concert of his music was arranged by his wife Meira in 1965 and was presented in Carnegie Recital Hall, New York City.
Most of the correspondence is of a personal nature, primarily family material. Pimsleur's widow continued to add to it after her husband's death in 1962. The Press Book, included in the papers, contains clippings pertaining to Pimsleur's career as well as a few letters of interest, notably from Vincent d'Indy, Rubin Goldmark, Dmitri Mitropoulos and Willem Mengelberg. The musical sketches provide a mass of fragments and scraps of paper, with little apparent order or identification. There are virtually no complete scores in the second series, but a number of scores are included on microfilm in series III. Series IV encompasses a set of paintings and drawings by an unknown hand.
As acquired, the collection had no inherent order. The current arrangement was imposed by the processor. The collection is arranged in four series: Correspondence and Papers, Sketches and Scores, Tapes and Microfilms, and Oversize.
This collection is open for research use.
The papers of Solomon Pimsleur were placed by Dr. Hans Moldenhauer, of Spokane, in the Moldenhauer Archives at Washington State University Libraries in August 1982.
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the online catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search the catalog using these headings.
Pimsleur, Solomon, 1900-1962--Archives; Moldenhauer, Hans
Composers--United States--Correspondence
Performing Arts; International Relations
The following section contains a detailed listing of the materials in the collection.
- Series 1: Correspondence and Papers, 1918-1970
  - Correspondence:
    - 1918-1939, 150 (Box 1, Folder 1-2)
    - 1940-1949, 150 (Box 1, Folder 3-4)
    - 1950-1959, 150 (Box 1, Folder 5-6)
    - 1960-1970, 70 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - undated, 150 (Box 1, Folder 8-9)
  - Papers:
    - 1918-1939, 30 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - 1940-1949, 40 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - 1950-1959, 200 (Box 1, Folder 12-14)
    - 1960-1970, 50 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - College papers, undated; 50 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Papers, undated; 100 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Press Book, 1920-1962; 1 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Programs and Reviews, 1914-1962; 70 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Posthumous concert, 1965; 10 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Catalogue of original compositions, 1974; 2 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Catalogue of works at Columbia University, 1974-1975; 1 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Poetry, 1918-1928; 30 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Poetry sketches, 1960-1961; 50 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Poetry sketches, undated; 150 (Box 2, Folder 25-26)
    - Photographs, 1924; undated; 30 (Box 2, Folder 27)
- Series 2: Sketches and Scores
  - Sketches:
    - Op. 2, op. 8, 2 (Box 3, Folder 28)
    - Op. 3, 10 (Box 3, Folder 29)
    - Op. 4, 28, 41, 53-56, 58, 10 (Box 3, Folder 30)
    - Op. 4#3, 14#5, 36#1, 7 and 10, 10 (Box 3, Folder 31)
    - Op. 5, 8, 9, 50, 50 (Box 3, Folder 32)
    - Op. 6, 20 (Box 3, Folder 33)
    - Op. 12, op. 13, 5 (Box 3, Folder 34)
    - Op. 14, op. 36, 30 (Box 3, Folder 35)
    - Op. 16, 50 (Box 3, Folder 36)
    - Op. 19, 50 (Box 3, Folder 37)
    - Op. 21, 30 (Box 3, Folder 38)
    - Op. 22, 50 (Box 3, Folder 39)
    - Op. 23, 20 (Box 3, Folder 40)
    - Op. 24, 30 (Box 3, Folder 41)
    - Op. 25 (earlier op. 22), 50 (Box 3, Folder 42)
    - Op. 30, 40 (Box 3, Folder 43-44)
    - Op. 30 and 35, 30 (Box 3, Folder 45)
    - Op. 31, 30 (Box 3, Folder 46)
    - Op. 33, 50 (Box 3, Folder 47)
    - Op. 35, 50 (Box 3, Folder 48)
    - Op. 40, 50 (Box 3, Folder 49-50)
    - Op. 42, 50 (Box 3, Folder 51)
    - Op. 44, 50 (Box 4, Folder 52)
    - Op. 45, 100 (Box 4, Folder 53-54)
    - Op. 46, 100 (Box 4, Folder 55-56)
    - Op. 48 and op. 52, 100 (Box 4, Folder 57-58)
    - Op. 49 and op. 52, 30 (Box 4, Folder 59)
    - Op. 50, 150 (Box 4, Folder 60-61)
    - Op. 51, 50 (Box 4, Folder 62)
    - Op. 59, 30 (Box 4, Folder 63)
    - Op. 60, 100 (Box 4, Folder 64-65)
    - Op. 61, #1 and #2, 60 (Box 4, Folder 66-67)
    - Op. 62, 30 (Box 4, Folder 68)
    - Op. 63, 66 and 71, 10 (Box 4, Folder 69)
    - Op. 64, 50 (Box 4, Folder 70)
    - Op. 66, 50 (Box 4, Folder 71)
    - Op. 67, 50 (Box 4, Folder 72)
    - Op. 68, 50 (Box 4, Folder 73)
    - Op. 69, 50 (Box 4, Folder 74)
    - Op. 70, 100 (Box 4, Folder 75-77)
    - Op. 74 and 75, 35 (Box 5, Folder 78-79)
    - Op. 77, 81-83, 86 and 88, 5 (Box 5, Folder 80)
    - Op. 90, 95, 102, 106, 5 (Box 5, Folder 81)
    - Anne Frank (opera), 250 (Box 5, Folder 82-88)
    - Revisions of early piano sonatas, 30 (Box 5, Folder 89)
    - Songs: Sonnets of Shakespeare, 10 (Box 5, Folder 90)
    - Unidentified Sketches, 200 (Box 5, Folder 91-93)
    - Unidentified Sketches, 200 (Box 6, Folder 94-99)
  - Scores:
    - Op. 24, Neo-classic Overture (parts), 20 (Box 6, Folder 100)
    - Op. 32, Tone-poem (parts), 20 (Box 6, Folder 101)
    - Photocopies and fragments, 10 (Box 6, Folder 102)
    - Meditative Nocturne, photocopy, 1 (Box 6, Folder 103)
    - Op. 75, transparencies, 1 (Box 6, Folder 104)
    - Piano Duet, MS fragment, 1 (Box 6, Folder 105)
    - Printed scores, 6 (Box 6, Folder 106)
- Series 3: Tapes and Microfilms, 1956-1965
  - Tapes (reel-to-reel):
    - Op. 1 and op. 7 (Box 6, Folder 107)
    - Op. 2 (Box 6, Folder 108)
    - Op. 5 (Box 6, Folder 109)
    - Op. 7 (Box 6, Folder 110)
    - Op. 15 (Box 6, Folder 111)
    - Op. 19 (Box 6, Folder 112-113)
    - Op. 20 and op. 29 (Box 6, Folder 114)
    - Op. 28 (Box 6, Folder 115)
    - Op. 29 (Box 6, Folder 116-117)
    - Concerts:
      - January 1, 1956, June 13, 1956 (Box 6, Folder 118)
      - January 23, 1957 (Box 6, Folder 119)
      - March 23, 1959 (Box 6, Folder 120)
      - February 21, 1965 (Box 6, Folder 121)
      - undated (Box 6, Folder 122)
    - Unidentified (Box 6, Folder 123-124)
  - Microfilms:
    - Op. 2, 34, 49, 76, 81-86 (Box 7, Folder 125)
    - Op. 12 and op. 28 (Box 7, Folder 126)
    - Op. 23 (Box 7, Folder 127)
    - Op. 26, 31, 37, 38, 39, 51-53, 57 (Box 7, Folder 128)
    - Op. 29, 32, 36, 48, 92, 96 (Box 7, Folder 129)
    - Op. 60 and op. 62 (Box 7, Folder 130)
    - Op. 70, 76, 77 (Box 7, Folder 131)
    - Op. 87, 89 (Box 7, Folder 132)
    - Op. 90 and op. 91 (Box 7, Folder 133)
    - Op. 90 and 100 (Box 7, Folder 134)
    - Opera, piano score (Box 7, Folder 135)
    - Opera, orchestral score, parts I and II (Box 7, Folder 136-137)
    - Works without opus number (Box 7, Folder 138)
    - Mournful Prelude (Box 7, Folder 139)
- Series 4: Oversize
  - Paintings and drawings, artist unknown, 12 (Box 7, Folder 140)